<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Information for Andrew Fletcher of Aberlady and his tutor against Sir Archibald Murray of Blackbarrony, and Sir Patrick Murray of Saltcoats and others.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 104KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 13 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09271</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">80922875</idno>
  <idno type="VID">191894</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240865597</idno>
  
            <idno type="OCLC"> 80922875</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing I163BB</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R188857</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">80922875</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09271)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 191894)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books; 1641-1700 ; 2894:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Information for Andrew Fletcher of Aberlady and his tutor against Sir Archibald Murray of Blackbarrony, and Sir Patrick Murray of Saltcoats and others.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>24 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Edinburgh? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard Law School Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Fletcher, Andrew.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Murray, Archibald, --  Sir.</term>
               <term type="personal_name">Murray, Patrick, --  Sir.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Guardian and ward --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Annuities --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Real property --  Scotland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-12 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <body>
         <div type="affidavit">
            <pb facs="tcp:191894:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:191894:1"/>
            <head>INFORMATION FOR <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> of <hi>Aberlady</hi> and his <hi>Tutor</hi> AGAINST <hi>Sir</hi> Archibald Murray <hi>of</hi> Blackbarrony, <hi>and Sir</hi> Patrick Murray <hi>of</hi> Saltcoats <hi>and Others.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>SIR <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> this Childs Grandfather having bought the Lands of <hi>Aberlady</hi> for 120000 Merks, from <hi>Hay</hi> Heretor thereof, with the Burden of an yearly Annuity of 2500. Merks payable yearly to <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> during her Lifetime: By the Transaction there were 42000 Merks of the price allowed to remain in Sir <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi>'s hand during the Lifetime of the said <hi>Jean Seaton,</hi> at least ay and while the Lands were Disbur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dened of the foresaid yearly Annuity.</p>
            <p>Sir <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> having thereafter dyed in the year 1675. And <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barrony</hi> and Sir <hi>Patrick Murray</hi> being elected Curators to his Son: The saids Curators, when their Pupil was about 16 years of Age, did enter into a most unwarrantable and disadvantageous Transaction with the said <hi>Jean Seaton</hi> and her Husband, for buying off of her said Liferent Annuity: By which they caused their Pupil with their Consent grant Bond to her and her Husband for the sum of 13000 Merks, as the price of that Annuity; albeit the said <hi>Jean Sea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> was then past 56. years of Age, and was Irrecoverably gone of a Cancer in her Breast; and whereof she died within a few Months after the Transaction. And about the same time when the Curators bought the Liferent Annuity her own Son <hi>William Hay</hi> was a buying of it, because he knew the burden of the Liferent lay upon his Fortune, and not upon <hi>Aberlady</hi>'s, who bought the Land with absolute Warrandice, the <hi>Hay</hi>'s Money being lyable for any Incumbrance that could come upon <hi>Fletcher</hi> of <hi>Aberlady,</hi> either by the Liferent, or any other manner of way: And the reason why her Son <hi>William Hay</hi> did not enter into a Bargain with his Mothers Husband <hi>Kennedy</hi> of <hi>Ardmillan</hi> for her Liferent Annui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, was the Information he had from his two Brothers <hi>Lewis</hi> and <hi>Hary Hays</hi> of his Mothers Condition, who had been Visiting their Mother, and she told them that she was dying of a Cancer, and given over by her Physicians: They also declared to <hi>William Hay</hi> their Brother, that they saw their Mothers Breast with a great Hole in it, and she told them that it was a Cancer, and that it was impossible for her to recover. And the Curators having given their own Bond
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:191894:2"/> of Corroboration to <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> and her Husband, for the foresaid Sum of 13000 Merks: And being conscious to themselves that the Pupil could not be in Law obliged to owne the forsaid Transaction after his Majority, they for their own Security allenerly against their Pupils quarrelling of that Transaction, induced and perswaded their Pupil to Ratify their said Transaction upon Oath. when he he was only about the foresaid Age of 16 Years: and shortly thereafter the Pupil Dyed before his Majority.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Blackbarronry</hi> having acquired Assignation to the Bond of 13000 Merks gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by himself and the other Curators, to <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> and her Husband for the price of her Life-rent Annuity, he did thereupon pursue <hi>Andrew Fletcher,</hi> now of <hi>Aberlady,</hi> for repayment of the foresaid Sum: And albeit there were se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Defences proponed by the said <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> and his Tutor for eleid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that pursute which are Humbly Conceived to be both Unanswerable and Relevant in Law; yet the Lords of Session did pronounce a Decreet sustaining the Transaction made by the Curators, and finding this <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> of <hi>Aberlady</hi> lyable in Repayment to them of the foresaid Sum of 13000 Merks: And as the said Decreet and hail Interloquitors in that process did not pass by an unanimous Vote of the Bench; so <hi>Aberlady</hi> and his Tutor apprehending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be Grieved and Laesed by the Interloquitors and Sentence by the Lords of Session, they did enter their Protestation for Remead of Law to the King and Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, against the foresaid Sentence and Interloquitors: And now with all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect and Deference to the Lords of Session, <hi>Aberlady</hi> is to insist before the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable and High Court of Parliament upon the Reasons of his Protestation and Appeal; and which are these. <hi>viz</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1<hi>mo.</hi> It is an uncontraverted principal in the Common Law, Ratified and Appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Consent and Practice of all Nations, That Curators are allenerly Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ministrators of their Pupils Means and Estate: And neither the Common Law, nor the Law of This, or any other Nation, doth allow Curators either to expend their Pupil's Means, or to cause their Pupils grant Bonds, or contract Debts for any Bargain or Transaction, wherein there is the least hazard of damnage and prejudice to ensue upon the account of such Transactions; but in case Curators at their own hand should engage either themselves, or their Pupils in any such Transactions, wherein there is the least hazard or prejudice to the Pupil, Law doth lay the Burden of all the Damnage, arising to the Pupil by such Transactions, upon the Curators themselves who made the same: And the Law hath been so cautious to secure Pupils against such Adventures of their Curators, that if any Benefit did eventually arise from that Transaction, the same did accresce to the Pupil; but if there did eventually happen or fall out any Damnage or prejudice to the Pupil, the same did alwayes ly and remain upon the Curators themselves: And the Law did alwayes allow the Pupil to be Reponed and Restored against such Transactions; in swa far as he became eventually to be thereby Laesed and prejudged: And the Reason of the Law is clear, because Curators having allen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerly a Right of Administration of their Pupil's Means and Estate, they ought to contain themselves within the Bounds and Limits of their Office of Curatry, and not at all to transgress the same by expending their Pupil's Means upon Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actions or Bargains, wherein the Loss and Gain therefrom arising are Uncertain, such as this Transaction was: And if any such Liberty should be allowed to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators, they might in a very short time dilapidat and exhaust all their Pupils E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states: And the Damnage arising by the Transaction to the Pupil is most palpable and exorbitant, the said <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> having dyed within few Months thereafter,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:191894:2"/> of a Disease whereof she was irrecoverably gone before the Transaction: So that all that the Pupil received for the said great Sum of 13000 Merks, was only one Terms Annuity of her Liferent, extending to 1250 Merks <hi>Scots</hi> only.</p>
            <p n="2">2<hi>do.</hi> The only Pretence alledged by the Curators for eleiding this Unanswer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Ground of Law, was, That they did act <hi>bona fide,</hi> having received no be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit to themselves, and designed nothing but the Pupils Advantage, and to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve him and his Estate of the Burden of such a considerable yearly Annuity which in process of time might have swallowed up all their Pupils Estate. And 2<hi>do.</hi> That the Pupil had ratified the Transaction made by his Curators upon Oath; And so his Heirs could never be allowed to quarrel the same, especially seeing the Transaction was rational at the time, and would have proven so in the event. if <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> had lived some few years, and that the Curators knew not that she was Labouring under such a Disease, at that time when the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action was made And 3<hi>tio.</hi> That this matter was <hi>res judicata</hi> between <hi>Ard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>millan</hi> and the Curators: All which pretences were most Irrelevant, and ought to have been Repelled by the Lords of Session.</p>
            <p n="1">1<hi>mo</hi> Because <hi>bona fides</hi> is only Competent to Defend or Excuse any Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action made, or Deeds done by persons Acting in their own Sphere; and within the bounds and limits of their own Office and Trust, and all persons are in <hi>mala fide</hi> to exceed or transgerss the Bounds and Limits of their own Trust: And no Lawyer or other person ever did pretend that any Curator, was allowed or im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered to expend or Dilapidat their Pupils certain Stock and effects upon such uncertain Bargains and Transactions: So that their making of that Transaction which <hi>ex eventu</hi> did prove so prejudicial to the Pupil, and which at the time was most uncertain at the best; was an most unwarrantable Act in them, and can allow of no species or pretence of <hi>bona fides:</hi> So as to defend or Excuse them from being Lyable to Repair their Pupil and his Heirs against the Damage arising to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil by the rash and unwarrantable Transaction made by themselves, as said is. 2<hi>do.</hi> Whatever Curators do, in <hi>re Pupillari</hi> contrair to Law and Incompetent and without the Trust of their Bounds and Offices can never be repute Rational or prudent, Law and the Bounds of their Office and Trust, being the outmost Limits set to Curators in the Management of their Pupils Affairs. 3<hi>tio.</hi> The pretence that the Curators knew not that <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> was Irrecoverably gone of an Disease, the time they made the Transaction, is so far from furnishing the Curators any Defence or Excuse, That <hi>Aberlady</hi> Retorts the same against the Curators, as a great Aggravation of their Malversation and Trangression of the Bounds of their Trust, and Office: Because it is a principle in Law that no man ought to be Ignorant of the Condition of these with whom he Bargains and Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acts. And certainly if any Barganer was in Law oblidged to inquire into the Condition of the person with whom he did Bairgain, these who Bargain for the Liferent of any person are oblidged to enquire into the Condition of the Health, Strength and Age of the person, for whose Liferent they are about to Transact: Especially Curators when Transacting for a Liferent to be purchased by their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils Means in case the Law had allowed Curators to m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ke such Transactions as it never did, so that as the said Transaction was unwarrantable, and beyond the Bounds of the Curators Office and Trust, so also the Curators were supinly Negligent in not sending to enquire into the Condition of <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi>'s Health before they had engaged for such an Exorbitant Sum as 13000 Merks for her Liferent: And their very negligence to enquire into the same is a separate Ground, and Relevant <hi>per se</hi> to make them Lyable to repair the Damage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rising
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:191894:3"/> to the Pupil through their negligence in not enquiring into the Condition of <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi>'s Health, before they entred into the said Transaction as in Law, and by the Trust reposed in them they were obliged to have done. 4<hi>to.</hi> The Pupil is not concerned whither the Curators had any Benifite or design of Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage to themselves or not, seeing the Transaction made by them not being war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranted by Law nor Incumbent to have being made by them as Curators <hi>virtute Officii:</hi> The same most be at the hazard of the Curators themselves, And no Law can make the Pupil Lyable to undergo the Damage, and prejudice arising by the Actings of his Curators contrair to Law and the Trust of their Offices as such. 5<hi>to.</hi> Law hath so strictly Limited Curators, that even upon emergent necessities they cannot transgress the Bounds of their Office without the sentence and warrand of an Soveraign Judicatur: As in the case of a Pupil his having seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ruinous Houses, the Curators cannot Legally Sell or Dispone upon one of these Ruinous Tenements without a Decreet of the Lords of Session, as was decid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Lords themselves in a case betwixt the Laird of <hi>Nidry</hi> and <hi>Sandilands,</hi> so that in caice there had been either necessity or Conveniency for the Curators to have made this rash and disadvantagious Transaction (as truely there was none) they ought previously to have applyed to the Lords of Session; and obtained their Decreet and warrand impowering and Authorizing them to do the same: But the Curators having no such Decreet of the Lords, it is evident the Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was made at her own hazard and perril and being against Law and without the Bounds of their Trust as Curators, the same can never be obtruded against the Pupil as an prudent and rational Transaction, so as to make him Lyable to ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifie the same and undergo the hazard of the Damage arising therefrom: And of all Curators in the World these Curators were in <hi>pessima fide</hi> to have entred into such a rash Transaction, seing there was als much of the price of the Lands left in <hi>Aberlady</hi>'s hands when the same was first purchased, as the Annual rents there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, would have defrayed and payed off <hi>Jean Seatouns</hi> yearly Annuity. And the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators never did, not yet can deny but there was als much of that Sum remaining unexhausted, as would have satisfied the said yearly Annuity for all the Years of their Pupil's Minority: And Curators being by the Office only obliged <hi>Rem Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilli salvam curare,</hi> they were only lyable &amp; obliged to preserve their Pupils Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition as it was the time of their Entry to the Office: And seing this Annuity could have been <hi>aliunde</hi> satisfied during all the Years of the Pupil's Minority, without contracting any new Debts upon the Pupil's Estate; it was sufficient for the Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to have entred the Pupil to a free Estate as his Father left him: and they were in <hi>pessima fide</hi> to have made such a Rash and Foolish Transaction, thereby burden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their Pupils Estate with a new Debt of 13000 Merks, and wherein their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil is so grosly and exorbitantly Laesed and prejudged, in case by the Justice of the Parliament he be not Reponed against the Sentence and Interloquitors of the Lords of Session.</p>
            <p>Neither is there any shadow of Relevancy in that other pretence of the Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, founded upon the Oath given by their Pupil; whereby he did Solemnly Swear never to quarrel, or come in the contrair of the Transaction made by the Curators, anent <hi>Jean Seatouns</hi> Life-rent Annuity, notwithstanding of the Text anent <hi>sacramenta puberum,</hi> alledged for fortifying of the said pretence; Because 1<hi>mo.</hi> There is no Nation in the World where that part of the Civil Law; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by a Minor being Laesed by a Transaction made by his Curators, is precluded from Restitution; and being Reponed against Transactions made by himself, or his Curators in his Minority, and to his palpable Hurt and Laesion, upon the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:191894:3"/> of an Oath, given by the Pupil in his Minority, never to quarrel the same, is in the least reguarded or observed; but on the contair there is not any Nation in <hi>Europe</hi> where the same is not expresly Reprobat by a Special Constitution and Municipal Law: And there is here in <hi>Scotland</hi> lately made an Act of Parliament, expresly Reprobating that part of the Civil Law, and appointing that no Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action made by a Minor to his enorme Laesion shall preclude him from being Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poned there against, notwithstanding that the Minor should by Oath oblige him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self never to quarrel the same; and declaring all Transactions and Obligations to which the Oath of a Minor is interposed to be Void and Null <hi>ipso jure,</hi> and in the Countrey of <hi>Friezland</hi> where the Civil Law is most observed, there is a Special statute that such Transactions as this, albeit ratified by the Minor upon Oath shall not be sustained or allowed, unless there be a previous sentence of a judge finding the Transaction to be Rational and profitable for the Minor; and impowering and Authorizing his Curators to make the same: And <hi>Blackbarrony</hi> and Sir <hi>Patrick Murray</hi> cannot alledge that there was any previous sentence of a judge impow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ering, and Authorizing them to enter into such a Transaction. 2<hi>do.</hi> The Oath given by the Deceast Laird of <hi>Aberlady</hi> in his Minority being in its self unjust and unwarrantable, as is above represented, could never have hindred him from quartelling the Transaction upon the head of Minority and eno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me Laesion, which is one of the Fundamental Principles of Equity it self, als well as of the Law of all Nations, allowed and confirmed by the practice of all Kingdoms in <hi>Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rope:</hi> But what ever might have been alledged against the deceast <hi>Aberla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> who gave that Oath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the account of Fame and Reputation, and being ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to Perjury in case of Contravention; yet no Man can contravert that the said Oath was only personal, and only obligator against the deceast <hi>Aberlady</hi> himself who gave the Oath: But the said <hi>Aberlady</hi> having died in his Minority, it is absurd to pretend that such an Oath which was only personal, and in it self most Unjust and Unwarrantable <hi>&amp; vinculum iniquitatis,</hi> should be obtruded to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude this <hi>Aberlady,</hi> who is his Heir, and who is yet an Infant, from Crav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be Reponed against such an Unjust Transaction, by which his For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune is in hazard of being utterly ruined, and undone: And all the Texts of the Civil Law alledged for the Curators do only Relate to the Minors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves who made the Oaths: But not at all to their Heirs and Successors. 3<hi>tio.</hi> Whatever <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> and her Husband to whom this 13000 Merks was ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to be payed by the foresaid Transaction could found or alledge upon the Deceast <hi>Aberladys</hi> Oath given in his Minority. Yet this is a principle in Law which no man will or can Contravert, That as all Deeds done by a Minor hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Curators without their consent are <hi>ipso jure</hi> null and void: So all Deeds done by Pupils in their Minority, in favours of their own Curators and for their behoof, and wherein the Curators are Authorising their Pupil to their own Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage <hi>&amp; in rem propriam,</hi> are likewayes <hi>ipso jure</hi> altogether void and null. But true it is that the Oath Elicite from the Deceast <hi>Aberlady</hi> by his Curators for Ratifying, the said Transaction was not at all elicite from him as a further security to <hi>Jean Seatoun,</hi> and her Husband to whom the said Sum of 13000 Merks was payable by this Transaction, they being abundantly, and unquesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onably secured anent the payment of the said Sum by a separat Bond of Corrobo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration granted by the Curators themselves, but on the contrair the said Oath was industriously elicite from the Minor by the Curators as a farther security to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves anent the said unwarrantable Transaction, and of purpose to preclude the the Pupil from quarrelling the same, and refusing to give them allowance of that
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:191894:4"/> Sum in their Accounts upon the unanswerable Grounds of Law competent to the Minor against them. <hi>viz.</hi> That the said Transaction was to his Enorme hurt and Laesion, and contrair to Law, and without any previous sentence or Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of a Judge, Authorizing them to make the same: And that it was without the Bounds of there Trust, and Office of Curatory to have entred into any such unwarrantable Transaction: So that the foresaid Oath being elicite from the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor Industriously by the Curators for their own Advantage and security, the same can never furnish the Curators any Defence against this Infant, who as Heir to their Pupil, craves to be Reponed against such unjust and prejudicial Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action upon the common known and uncontraverted principles, aswell of Equity as of the Law, of this and all other Nations under Heaven, where Law and Justice are known to have place. And as to that pretence that it was <hi>res judicata,</hi> Its An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swered 1<hi>mo</hi> That was <hi>res inter alios acta</hi> And 2<hi>do, Aberlady</hi> hath just Reason to suspect that there was some secret in that Affair since the Curators did not appear against <hi>Ardmillan,</hi> but left the Managment of that Affair to my Lord <hi>Mersing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toun,</hi> this <hi>Aberlady</hi>'s Grandfather, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> much as con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ance him at any consultatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ates: And yet they have the confidence to Charge the Pupil with 500 Merks spent in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Managment of that Business, tho they gave not out one Farthing about it, but my Lord <hi>Mersingtoun</hi> Debursed all.</p>
            <p>And for further convincing of their Majesties High Commissioner, And the Honourable Estates of Parliament, that the Grounds Above represented are founded upon true and solid Law and Reason: there is produced in the Clerks hands, The Opinions of the greatest and most eminent Professors of Law, both in <hi>Leyden</hi> and <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> Subscribed with their hands upon their Conscience, and sealed with the Seals of both Universities. <hi>As also there is produced the Opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of</hi> Amesius Perkins <hi>and</hi> Durham <hi>upon Oaths,</hi> wherein after an full and impartial state of the case, they give their Judgement, and agree Unanimously in this that the forsaid Transaction was contrair to Law, and without the Sphere and province of the Curators. And that the prejudice arising eventu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lly there upon <hi>ex post Facto,</hi> Ought to be laid upon the Curators themselves who made the said Transaction at their own hazard, and that the Oath elicite from the their Pupil in his Minority, neither could nor ought to prejudge the Minor, who gave the Oath or his Heirs from being Reponed against the said Transaction, in swa far as he was thereby any ways Laesed or prejudged. And they are so exact anent the Grounds of their said Opinion and Judgement, That they have set down a great Number of Citations out of all the eminent Lawyers that ever wrote upon that Subject aswell as several Texts out of the Civil Law it self for clearing that what is given by them as their Judgement is and hath been the clear and uncontraverted Opinion of all that other Lawyers before this time: And that the same is no new Fancy of their own, and it is craved for <hi>Aberlady</hi> that the Opinions of these Doctors given upon their Conscience, as said is, may be publickly read in plain Parliament, and whereof there is a just true and exact Translation hereto sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joined.</p>
            <p>And seing this Affair is of Universal Concern to all the Nation; and that the allowing Curators to make such Bargains at hazard upon their Pupils account, without any previous Cognition or Sentence of a Judge, would certainly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage all Curators to hazard all their Pupils <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>states, and put them in hazard of utter Ruine in their clear and free Fortunes: And that <hi>Aberlady</hi> humbly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceives the Interloquitors of the Session, pronounced in favours of the Curators, and debarring him from quarrelling of the said Transaction, will appear clearly from
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:191894:4"/> what is above represented to be down-right contrair to the uncontraverted Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the Law of all Nations, and Equity it self, as being unwarrantable and without the Sphere of the Curators Office and Trust, who have only a Right of Administration of their Pupils Means and not of Dominion and property; and that no Law allows Administrators to make Bargains of hazard; and that there was no preceeding Cognition, nor previous Sentence of a Judge; and that the Curators were supinely negligent, in not enquiring into the condition of <hi>Jean Seatouns</hi> Health before they made the Transaction for her Liferent; and that there was sufficient Remains of the price of the Lands for defraying that Annuity during the Pupil's Minority: As also, that the Oath elicite by them from their Pupil was <hi>in rem propriam,</hi> and for their own Advantage and Security alenerly: And that the Opinion of such Eminent Professors in <hi>Leyden</hi> and <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, do clear the Grounds aboverepresented to be unanswerable, <hi>Aberlady</hi> humbly expects from the Justice of the High and Honourable Court of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, that the Sentence and Interloquitors of the Session, pronounced against him in Favours of the Curators, will be Rescinded, and he Reponed against the Transaction made by the Curators, wherein his Predecessor was so grosly and pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pably Laesed.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="verdict">
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191894:5"/>
            <head>The Opinion of the Ʋniversity of ƲTRECHT.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="verdict">
               <head>Facti Species.</head>
               <p>D: <hi>Andreas Fletcher</hi> certo pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio sibi comparavit Territo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rium de <hi>Aberladie</hi> sed prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter constitutum Domine de <hi>Kennedo</hi> de <hi>Ardmillan,</hi> in territorio illo usum fructum id inter emptorem &amp; venditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orem expressa fuit actum pactione ut penes emptorem usu fructu durante residua remaneret ex pretio promisso quantitas 42000 Marcarum, quo posset existius pecuniae usuris annuis ex more regionis ad bis mille quingen. tas Marcas ascendentibus prestati to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tidem marcarum quot usu fructuariae annuatim jure usus fructus erant ex sol vendae, mortuo deinde emptore re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licto filio minorenne <hi>Archibaldo Flet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> Curatores ejus Domini de <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barronny</hi> &amp; alii transigerunt cum Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mina usu fructuaria annum aetatis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gente sextum &amp; quinquesimum ac ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nero tunc laborante ut illa acceptis si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mul ac semel tredecem marcarum millibus jus suum usus fructus Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no proprietatis minorenni cederet at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que ita omni juri servitutis renunciaret in hujus autem transactionis securita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Curatores spoponderunt acpropri am devinxerunt personam atque insu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Pupillo suo autores fuerunt ut ille annum agens aetatis septimum &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cimum jurejurando solemni promitte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ret se illam transactionem ratam habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turum, nec unquam eandem inpug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturum. Fructuaria his gestis bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vi post ex cancro extincta fuit, ipse quoque minor fato functus successo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem habuit fratris sui filium <hi>Andre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Fletcher</hi> ad huc impuberem. Huic cum per Curatores defuncti lis
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:191894:5"/> mota fuit ad restitutionem 13000 Marcarum transactione comprehensa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, quas illi ex suo ajebant esse ex solutas, succubit impuber iu supremo <hi>Scotiae</hi> consessa juridico denegata ei quam ex defuncti patrui capite im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plorabat restitutione in integrum ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versus transactionem defuncti Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris nomine per Curatores defuncti cum fructuatia initam &amp; ab ipso Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nore defuncto per jusjurandum firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam, ab ea vero sententia ad Parlia<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mentum <hi>Scoticanum</hi> impuberis nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne ex more jurcque concessa fuit ap<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>pellatum: Ad hanc facti speciem duo potissimum quaesita fuerunt.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Primo,</hi> An Curatores, talem transactionem (vel potius Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem) legitime inite potuerunt.</p>
               <p n="2">2do. An si ipso Jure valeret, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor contra eam in integrum restitui non posset</p>
               <p>Nos infra scripti Professores Juris constituentes facultatem Juridicam in Accademia <hi>Trajectina,</hi> conside<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantes facti speciem questionesque ex ea propositas, ita judicavimus.</p>
               <p>Quoad primam Questionem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suasi sumus Curatores non potuisse ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem Transactionem inite sed ipso Jure nullam esse.</p>
               <p>Nam licet verum sit, Transactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem permitti Tutoribus &amp; Curatori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus non eam tamen inire possunt qua Jus liquidum Pupillorum remittunt. <hi>L.</hi> 54 §. <hi>fin: L.</hi> 56. §. 4 <hi>ff. de furtis</hi> aut eam perquam Jus Minorum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minuitur <hi>L</hi> 46 § <hi>fin: ff. de Adm: &amp; peric: tut:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Tunc Demum Curatori permititur Transactio ubi res obscura est &amp; liti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giosa in judicium deducta, ut ex ore judicis decisio litis pendeat, ubi dubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us &amp; incertus litis eventus aliquid ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipere vel remittere potius quam de toto venire in periculum suadet <hi>Bach: ad Trutl: vol:</hi> 1. <hi>Disp:</hi> 7. <hi>th.</hi> 2. <hi>Gail L.</hi> 2. <hi>obs:</hi> 72.</p>
               <p>Tutor quidem loco Domini est, L. 27. <hi>de Admi: &amp; per: tut:</hi> eique suffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191894:6"/> si in re Pupilli tanqnam bonus pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter familias versetur L. 33. ff: eodem. unde consequens videretur recte Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratotes in casu proposito Tranfactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fecisse cum etiam patres familias qui ipsi frugi &amp; proprietarii sunt saepe onus usus fructus redimere solent.</p>
               <p>Animadvertandum tamen quod re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vera Domini non sunt. sed tales tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum habentur quatenus Minori utilia fecerunt, Montan: de Tutel: Cap: 31. eff: 1. U: 21.</p>
               <p>Neque enim omne id quod Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no in re sua permissum sit, id Tutori quoque licet in re Pupillari.</p>
               <p>Dominus quidem rei suae liber Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derator est, atque Arbiter, L. 21. C. Mand. Sed id de Tutore dici nequit cujus Administratio restricta est at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que limitata: Culpam nemo prestat in re propria quam Tutor tamen pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stat in re Pupilli, L. 1. ff: de Tutel. &amp; Ration: Distra: Unde cautius &amp; pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentius res Pupillares tractare debet quam suas sicut &amp; maritus res dotales, L. 24. <hi>ss</hi> 5. ff. solut. Matrim. Faber Juris. P: Papin. tit. 12. prin: 7. illat. 43.</p>
               <p>Nullas dubitat quin Mercator mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces suas pecuniamve ad Merces com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parandas dubiis Maris fluctibus ac tempestatibus insidiosis, piratatum ex cursionibus spe majoris lucri expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere possit, id ipsum tamen Tutori per se integrum non esse constat ex L. 58 pr. ff. de Adm. &amp; per. tut.</p>
               <p>Alii Mercium transvehendarum periculum pro certo pretio, (assecura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem vocant) in se recipiunt quod tamen Tutori licere nemo dixetit, &amp; sex centa similia in medium proferii possent.</p>
               <p>Ut nullo modo Tutor culpa exima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur si tale quid circa res Pupillares ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miserit, quod forte in propriis quo{que} negotiis admiteret.</p>
               <p>Cujus rei decisio, elegans &amp; maxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me ad rem subjectam opposita, extat in Mevii decis. part. 4. decis. 9, Ubi Judicatum refert Tutorem etiam si
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191894:6"/> bonam sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m de lucrando Majori pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio haberet, &amp; ideo Pupilli frumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum aeque ac suum non vendiderat ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men intellecto damno quod praevide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re potuisser Tutorem teneri &amp; lucri incerti spem arguere ejus imprudenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am quam etiam arguit praeceps festi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natio. L. 7. <hi>ss</hi> 1. ff de Adm &amp; per. tut.</p>
               <p>Denique non adversatur nostrae sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientiae quod Curatores possint praedia Pupillaria servitutibus quibus obno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xia sunt liberate.</p>
               <p>In realibus enim servitutibus id pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedit non autem in personalibus in illis quia ipsis prediis inhaerent perpetuo.</p>
               <p>Secus quam in personalibus quae morte extinguntur, atque ita in nostra casu potuisset morte usu fructuariae statim extingui usus fructus, cur ergo Curatores 13000 Marcas, solvunt pro consolidatione quam praevidere pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, futuram sine ea sortis diminuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>one ita jam causa sunt damni Pupilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris: Perinde ac si cum alio sponsio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem ini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssent sub spe probabilis lucri quae tamen spes fallere posset.</p>
               <p>Nonne hoc est res Pupillares expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere fortuitis casibus citra necessita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem? Nonne melius fuisset conser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vare quod Pupillus habet quam rem dubii eventus aleae committere? Et cum Curarores existis 13000 Marca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum potuissent certiores percipere redditus, cur non perciperunt? Cur eam sortem perdiderunt, tenentur er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go de non perceptis quae percipere certius potuissent. L. 32. <hi>ss</hi> 2. ff. de Adm: &amp; per: tut.</p>
               <p>Concludimus itaque cum Curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res potestatis limites egressi fuerunt, certam sortem incerti lucri eventui ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponentes, de rei Pupilli certa &amp; liqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da sine Authoritate Magistratus tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sigentes ipsam Transactionem ipso Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re null am esse. Quod ad altetam que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stionem spectat an Minor contra pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictam Transactionem non posset re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitui in integrum.</p>
               <p>Respondemus etiamsi quis suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nere vellet Transactionem dictam ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191894:7"/> jure valere, non obstantibus prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictis rationibus quae contrarium sua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent Minori tamen restitutionis auxi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium non esse denegandum, certum enim absque omni contradictione Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norem nostrum ex dicta Transactione damnum esse passum non leve 13000 Mercarum.</p>
               <p>Juris autem est non contraversi Minoribus laesis dare restitutionem Tot: tit: ss: &amp; Cod: de restit: Minor. Etiamsi Tutorem aut Curatorem au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritas intervenerit L. 2. Cod: si Tutor.</p>
               <p>Quodtanta magis nostro casu est ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittendum cum pateat hoc damnum Pupillo datum esse, non casu fortuito sed culpa ipsorum Curatorum, nam sicuti is qui transigit de alimentis tanquam de re favorabili, ita Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor quoque transigens pro Pupillo tanquam persona imprimis favorabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li inquirere debet, in causam &amp; mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum Transactionis ut &amp; in personam transigentis. Arg. L. 8. <hi>ss.</hi> 8. ff. de Transact: Gail. L. 2. Ob: 72.</p>
               <p>In culpa igitur fuerunt Curatores quod non inquisiverint in causam Transactionis an necessaria esset?</p>
               <p>Talis autem non erat ut supra di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum a contrario nihil potuisset tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus Imputari, si pupilli jus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquissent in eo statu in quod invene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, presertimcum pactio Patris magnam summam pro usu fructu reti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nentis nullo modo camnosa erat Pupillo, sed expositio 13000 Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carum luctuosissimum damnum Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillo attulit.</p>
               <p>Non autem Pupillo debet nocere factum Tutoris qui aliquid ex sorte Pupilli Citra urgentem necessitatem vel honestatem erogavit Mar. decis 199. part 7.</p>
               <p>In super in culpa fuerunt Curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res quod non inquisiverint in perso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam usu fructuariae, cum qua transi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gere volebant innotescre enim ipsis potuisset, quod usu fructuaria jam na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta annos sex ultra quam quiquaginta,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:191894:7"/> insuperetiam in valitudine admodum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firma utebatur, periculosissimo cancti laboran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e morbo, à medicis jam tum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licta, ut nullo modo Consulti foret tan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum summam etogare: pro usu fructu in corpore tam debili constituto.</p>
               <p>Quod si ita eos latuerint Negligentiae certe eorum id imputari debet, cum di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligentiore Inquisitione facta scire potuis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent, &amp; debuissent conditionem ejus cum qua transactionem inituri essent <hi>Arg. L.</hi> 19. <hi>de reg. Juris.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Denique hoc vel maxime eorum cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pam Arguit, quod (ut exactis nobis sug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gestum est) cum per duos Juris peritos moniti essent de transactionis talis peri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culo, nihil ominus transigere voluerint, idque non pretermisserent quo pro se &amp; pupillo tutissime facere potuissent, nam vel tunc tutor Authoritatem male Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ponit; quando dubium est an res pupillo exped<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at, <hi>Ad. Mar. Decis</hi> 72. <hi>part</hi> 8.</p>
               <p>Contra nostram Sententiam admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum facere videtur Jusjurandum sollen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne à minore prestitutum, quo promisit se nunquam cont<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>a praedictam trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionem venturum, adeoque abomni restitutionis remedio exclusus videtur. pr. l. 1. &amp; Decantatum Auth: Sacramen: puberum Cod: Si adv. vend.</p>
               <p>Verum Ita nobis non videtur, non pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo ex tersiorum interpretum sententia Jus jurandum Minoris non potest con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmare actus ipo jure nullos Arg: l 5 C. de lib. nisi quis minorum conditionem multo pejorem facere vellet quam majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum.</p>
               <p n="2">2do. Non potest Jusjurandum minori prejudicare, ratione curatorum quando quidem eorum authoritate prestitum sit. autores in re propria fuerunt, quae autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritas nulla est, ss. fin: inst. de autor. tutor. L. 1. L. 7. F. eodem Tanto magis cum astute videntur id hoc casu egisse, mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niti enim de periculo transactionis pro qua ipsi fidem interposuerint ipsi autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res fuerunt pupillo praestandi Jurisjuran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di ut eo magis ipsis esset cautum, atque eo ipso se ipsos videntur arguere Curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res quod contractum Juramento Mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris voluerint confirmare.</p>
               <p n="3">3tio. Denique predictam Auth: om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nium Europeorum consuetudine abro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatam
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:191894:8"/> esse testantur omnes qui de mori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus scripserint quorum lurimi citantur. A Groenob. ad D. Auth: Atque in ipsa quoque Scotia ad ipsum receptum esse ex actis nobis suppeditatum est, optima sane ratione quia ut erudite observat mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macius ad D. Auth. in Observatione Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brico nonne ut in Levi glacie prima illa aetas facillime Labitur vertitur motatur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que, huc illuc tanquam fluvialis arundo ne{que} debet misellus paenas luere suae In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentiae.</p>
               <p>Quod si tandem Curatores querantur se expendisse tantam summam pro pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillo, Imputent sibi quod Damnum Cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pa &amp; imprudentia sua Senserint, neque in omnem eventum id pupillo imputan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, sed videndum foret An si decepti sint ipsis non potius Consuli posset, vel <hi>actione empti,</hi> vel <hi>in factum,</hi> Adversus haeredes usu fructuariae quae tantam sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mam pro redemptione usu fructus per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepit, cum sciere<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> se cancio Laborari &amp; Amedicis relictam &amp; charam sibi fata<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem identidem expectare, Arg: l: 11. ss. 5. de act. empti l. 11. ss. 1. F. de dolo.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Ita Consulti examini Sententia re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondimus, atque in fidem huic respon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>so subscripsimus id{que} minore Accade<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mico sigillo munivimus Trajecti ad Rhenum <date>die 4/14 <hi>May</hi> 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic subscribitur,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>L. Vandepoll <hi>Jur: Pros: Ʋitraj:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Johann: van Muijden 1693. J. V. D. &amp; <hi>Proff:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Locus Sigilli</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:191894:5"/>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="verdict">
               <head>The State of the Affair.</head>
               <p>SIR <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> for a certain Sum of Money Bought the Estate of <hi>Aberlady,</hi> But because of a setled Liferent of the Lady <hi>Kennedy</hi> of <hi>Ardmil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> on that Estate, it was agreed upon by express paction betwixt the Buyer and the Seller, that during the Liferent there should remain in the Buyers hands the Sum of 42000 Merks that the yearly interest thereof amounting to 2500 Merks might compense the equivalent Sum that was to be payed yearly to the said Liferentrix by her Liferent Right: The Buyer Dying thereafter, left <hi>Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bald Fletcher</hi> his Son a Minor, whose Curators the Laird of <hi>Blackbarrony,</hi> and others Transacted with the Liferentrix (going in the fiftieth and sixth year of her Age, and at that time Sick of a Cancer) that upon payment of 13000 Marks to her, she should quite her Liferent Right, in Favours of the Heretour being Minor, and so Renounce all Right of Servitude and Interest she had: In security of which Transaction the Curators engaged, and personally bound and obliged them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; and likewise caused their Pupil running in the Seventeenth year of his Age, to promise by his Solemn Oath, to ratify the said Transaction, and never come in the contrary. Things being thus carryed on, the Liferentrix shortly after Dyed of a Cancer, and the Minor likewise Deceased, to whom succeeded <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> his Brothers Son a Minor too. Him the defuncts Curators pursued for Restitution of 13000 Merks contained in the Transaction, which they alleged was payed out of their own Money: The cause being debate before the Lords</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:191894:5"/>
               <p>The Minor succumbred, the Lords refus<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Repone him which he pleaded for, on the Account of the Defunct, his Uncle against a Transaction made in name of the Defunct a Minor by the Defuncts Curators with the Liferentrix, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Deceast Minor himself by an Oath: From this Sentence an Appeal was made to the Parliament of <hi>Scotland</hi> in name of the said <hi>Andrew Fletcher:</hi> In this case two things were especially enquired into.</p>
               <p n="1">1. If the Curators could lawfully enter in such a Ttransaction or rather Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?</p>
               <p n="2">2. Supposing the Transaction to be Relevant in Law, Whither the Minor might not be Reponed to his former State contrare to it?</p>
               <p>We the Professors of Law constitut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the faculty of Law in the Colledge of <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> under Subscribing, Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dering the the state of the Affair, and the Questions proposed from it have so judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
               <p>As to the first Question, We are per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded that the Curators could not enter in such Transaction, and that <hi>ipso jure</hi> it is null.</p>
               <p>For although it be true that Tutors and Curators are permitted to Transact, Yet they cannot engage therein, so as to Remit the clear and manifest Right of their Pupils <hi>l.</hi> 54 <hi>ss. fin. l.</hi> 56 <hi>ss.</hi> 4. <hi>ff de furtis.</hi> Or in a transaction where the Right of Minors is diminished <hi>l</hi> 46 <hi>ss. fin de Adm &amp; per. tut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But then only is a Curator permitted to Transact, when a thing that is obscure and litigious is brought into Judgemennt that the Decision of the controversy may be determined dy the mouth of the Judge. Where the event of a debate may seem doubtful or uncertain, it will be better to take something rather than come into the hazard of the whole <hi>Bach ad Trutl. Vol. Disp.</hi> 7. <hi>Th.</hi> 2. <hi>lit.</hi> E. <hi>Gail l</hi> 2. <hi>Obs</hi> 72.</p>
               <p>A Tutor indeed is instead of a Master or Owner <hi>l</hi> 27. <hi>de Adm &amp; per tut.</hi> And
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:191894:6"/> it may suffice if he carry on his Pupils Affair as a good Proprietors <hi>l.</hi> 3. <hi>ff. eodem.</hi> Whereby it might seem to follow, that the Curators did Transact a Right in the case proposed, since even Masters of Families who are Frugal and Proprietars use of times to redeem the Burden of Liferent.</p>
               <p>Yet it is to be observed that they are not really Proprietors but are only e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>steemed such in so far as they shall do things profitable for the Minor. <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan de tutel. Cap.</hi> 31. <hi>eff.</hi> 1. <hi>u</hi> 21.</p>
               <p>Neither is all that a Proprietor or Owner may do in his own Affair permit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to a Tutor in the Affair of his Pupil.</p>
               <p>For a Proprietor is the free Orderer and Diposer of his own Estate <hi>L:</hi> 21. <hi>C. Mand.</hi> But that cannot be said of a Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor whose Administration is restricted and limited.</p>
               <p>None is Lyable for Mismanagement in his own matter, But a Tutor is Lyable in the matter of his Pupil <hi>L:</hi> 1. <hi>ff: de tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel &amp; ration distrah.</hi> So that he ought to order the Affairs of his Pupil more warily and prudently than his own: As must a Husband the things that relate to his Wives Dowry <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>ss.</hi> 5 <hi>ff solut Matrini Faber Jurisp. Papin. tit.</hi> 12. <hi>print.</hi> 7. <hi>ill.</hi> 43. No man doubts but a Merchant may expose his Waires, or Money for Buying of Waires, to the doubtful Sea Waves and Tempests, and the hazardous excursions of Pirats on the hope of greater Gain; whereas it would not be safe for a Tutor by himself to do the same. <hi>Ex l.</hi> 58 <hi>pr. ff de Adm. &amp; per. tut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Others take upon them the peril of of Transporting Waires for a certain Sum of Money which they call <hi>Ensuring,</hi> But I hope none will say that a Tutor may the same, Thousands of the like like nature might be adduced: so that a Tutor cannot be blameless, if he should do in his Pupils Affairs, perhaps as he would do in his own proper Business.</p>
               <p>An excellent decision whereof and most apposite to present Subject is to be
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:191894:6"/> seen in <hi>Maev. decis. part</hi> 4. <hi>decis.</hi> 9. Where he tells us it was determined that a Tutor who had good hopes of getting a price afterward, and upon that head did not sell his Pupils Corn, as also he did his own, but finding the Damnage that followed thereupon which might have been forseen, the Tutor was made Lyable and the hope of uncertain Gain did only bewray his imprudence, the like doth too great hast and Praecipitance <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>ss.</hi> 1. <hi>ff. de Adm &amp; per tut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lastly, It doth not cross our sentence that Curators can free their Pupils Lands from Servitudes, to which they were Lyable. For that only holdeth in real Servitudes but not in personal, In those because they are perpetually inherent in the very Lands contrare to personal Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vitudes, which are extinguished by Death, and so in our case the Liferent might have been immediatly extinguish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Death of the Liferentrix. Wherefore then did the Curators pay 13000 Merks for consolidation which they might foresee would come to pass without that lessening of the Stock, so now they are the cause of their Pupils Loss, even as if they had entted in Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain with another under the hopes of greater profite, which hope for all that might deceave them.</p>
               <p>Is not this to expose the Pupils Goods to Fortuitous, Chances without nny necessity? Had it not been better to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>serve what the Pupil has then to put his Estate to the hazard of a doubtful event? And seeing the Curators by those 13000 Merks might have received more certain profits, why did they not receive them? How came they to loss that Stock? Therefore they are Lyable for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits not received which they might have more cettainly received <hi>l.</hi> 32. <hi>ss. ff. de Adm &amp; per tut.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Therefore we conclud that when Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators go beyond the Limits of their power, And expose the Stock that is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain to the event of uncertain Gain, Transacting in the Estate of their Pupi
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:191894:7"/> that is certain and Liquid, and that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the Authority of the Majistrate; that that Transaction <hi>is ipso jure</hi> void and null.</p>
               <p>As to the other Qustion, Whether the Minor may not be restored to his fomer state contrare to the foresaid Transaction</p>
               <p>We Answer, that tho one should sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the former Transaction to be valid in Law (notwithstanding of the foresaid Reasons we have proponed in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary) yet the Minor should not be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyed the help of Restitution.</p>
               <p>For it is certain without any Contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction that our Minor by the said Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acion has suffered no small Damage of 13000 Merks; And it is incontravert<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ible in Law that wronged Minors should have Restitution <hi>tot. tit. ff. &amp; Cod. de Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stit.</hi> Minor. altho the Authority of Tutors and Curators interveen <hi>l,</hi> 2, <hi>Cod, Si Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor vel Cur, Interv.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Which is so much the more to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted in our case, since it is known that this Damage was done to the Pupil not by any accidental chance, but by the fault of the Curators themselves.</p>
               <p>For as he who Transacts about ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment as a favourable matter, so a Tutor likewise Transacting for his Pupil as a person most favourable, ought to enquire into the cause and manner of the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, as also into the person of the Transacter <hi>Arg, l,</hi> 8, <hi>ss,</hi> 8, <hi>ff de Transact. Gail l.</hi> 2. <hi>obs</hi> 72. <hi>m.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Curators therefore were to blame that they did not enquire into the cause of the Transaction, whether it were necessary?</p>
               <p>But this was not so as we have heard; yea upon the contrair nothing could have been imputed to the Tutors if they had left the Pupils Right in that conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in which they found it, especially since the Fathers Paction who keeped a great Sum in his own hand for the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent could no ways be hurtful to the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pil, but the exposing of 13000 Merks brought a most lamentable loss to the Pupil.</p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:191894:7"/>
               <p>But the Deed of a Tutor who layeth out any thing of the Pupils Stock, with: out any urgent necessity or Honesty, should no wayes prejudge the Pupil: Mar: Decis: 199. part 7.</p>
               <p>Moreover the Curators were to blame that they did not inquire into the person of the Liferentrix, with whom they were willing to Transact: For it might have easily been made known to them that a Woman of fifty and six years of Age, and very valetudinary and infirm, labouring under a most pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rilous Dilease, <hi>viz.</hi> a Cancer, and given over by the Physicians could not live long, so that it was very unadvised and inconsiderate to bestow so great a sum for a Liferent, standing in the person of so weak a Body as Hers.</p>
               <p>But if those things were unknown to them, yet at least it is to be imputed to their Negligence, who if they had made a more diligent search and inquiry, they both might and ought to have known her condition with whom they were to Transact, Arg: l. 19: de Reg: Juris.</p>
               <p>But lastly, this above all renders them guilty that (as we are informed by Writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings) when they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e forewarned of the hazaad of such a Transaction by two Lawyers; that notwithstanding they would Transact and not leave it undone, which might have made most safely for themselves and their Pupil. For even then the Tutor interposetth his Authority amiss, when it is doubtful whether the thing will be expedient for the Pupil or not? <hi>Addit: ad Mar. Decis:</hi> 72 <hi>part</hi> 3.</p>
               <p>But this may seem to make against our Sentence very strongly, that the Minor did Swear a Solemn Oath that he should never come in opposition to, nor contraveen the foresaid Transaction, and therefore may seem to be excluded from all remedy of Restitution, <hi>pr l.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; decantatum Auth: Sacrament: puberum Cod: si adv: vend:</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But it seemeth not so unto us,</p>
               <p>For 1<hi>mo.</hi> According to the Opinion of the best of Interpreters the Oath of a Minor can no ways confirm these Acts. that are <hi>ipso jure</hi> null. <hi>Arg. l.</hi> 5. <hi>C: de lib.</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:191894:8"/> unless one would make the condition of Minors worse than that of Majors.</p>
               <p n="2">2<hi>do.</hi> That Oath cannot prejudge the Minor on the account of the Curators, since it was given by their Authority: They were Authors in their own matter, which Authority is null, <hi>fin. inst de au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor tutor l:</hi> 1. <hi>l.</hi> 7. <hi>ff eodem.</hi> So much the more when they seem craftily to have done it in this case, for being warned of the hazard of the Transaction wherein they were engaged, they perswaded their Pupil to give his Oath that they might be the more secure. And by the same the Curators seem to accuse themselves in desiring that Contract to be confirmed by the Minors Oath.</p>
               <p n="3">3<hi>tio.</hi> To conclude the foresaid Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick is abrogated by the Custome of all Europ, as all testify who have written of manners and Customs, whereof ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny are cited by <hi>Groenovius ad</hi> D. <hi>Auth.</hi> And even in <hi>Scotland</hi> it self as we are in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by the pubick Records, this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived: And that upon very good Reason. For as <hi>Momacius</hi> learnedly observes <hi>ad</hi> D. <hi>Auth.</hi> In the slipperiness of Youth, does not that first Age, as on smooth Ice easily slide, is easily turned, wagged and shaken hither and thither like a Reed in a Marish or River; whether ought the poor wretch to suffer for the punishment of his own innocence.</p>
               <p>But if the Curators at last should com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain and say that they have laid out so great a Sum for their Pupil they may blame themselves for any Damage they have felt through their own fault and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prudence: Neither is a Pupil to be charged upon every event. But they ought to have considered if they were deceived, Whither they might not have had Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dress either by an Action against the Buyer, or upon the Fact against the Heirs of the Liferentrix, who received so great a Sum for the Redemption of the Liferent, when she knew that she was Labouring under a Cancer, and given over by the Phycisians, and every hour expecting Death. <hi>Arg. l.</hi> 2, <hi>ss.</hi> 5 <hi>de Act. empt. l.</hi> 11. <hi>ss.</hi> 1. <hi>ff de dolo.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Being thus advised we have given our Answer upon our Conscience, In testi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony whereof we have Subscribed the same and affixt thereto the lesser Seal of the Colledge of <hi>Ʋtrecht</hi> on the Rhine <date>
                        <hi>May</hi> 4/14. 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic subscribitur.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>L. Vandepoll <hi>jur: Prof: Ʋltraj:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Johan: van Muyden J. V. D. &amp; <hi>Proff.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="verdict">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:191894:8"/>
            <head>The Opinion of the Ʋniversity of LAYDEN.</head>
            <div xml:lang="lat" type="verdict">
               <head>Facti Species.</head>
               <p>EXActorum Scoticanorum, in lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guam Latinam Translatorum Exemplis Exhibitis cum facti Species haec apparuerit, Dominum <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draeam Fletcher</hi> certo pretio sibi com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parrasse territorium <hi>Aberlady,</hi> sed prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Constitutum Dominae de <hi>Kennedo</hi> de <hi>Ardmillan</hi> in territorio illis usum fructum, Id inter venditorem emptorem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que expressa fuisse actum pactione ut penes emptorem usu fructu durante resi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dua temaneret ex pretio promisso quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titas 42000 Mercarum quo posset ex istius pecuniae usuris annuis ex more regionis Ad 2500 Marcas ascendentibus prestare totidem marcarū quantitas an nuatim usu fructuariae x jure usu fructus debita &amp; ex solvenda. Mortuo dein emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore relicto filio Minorenne <hi>Archibaldo Fletcher</hi> Curatores ejus Dominum de <hi>Blackbarrony</hi> &amp; alios transegisse cum Domina fructuaria annum aetatis agente 56 ac Cancro tunc laborante, ut illa acceptis simul &amp; semel 13000 Marca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, jus suum usu fructus Domino pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietatis Minorenni Cederet atque ita omni renunciaret Juri servitutis. In hujus autem transactionis securitatem Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores spopondisse ac propriam devinx<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>isse personam: At que in super pupillo suo autores fuisse ut ille annum aetatis agens septimum &amp; decimum jure juran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>do sollenni promitteret se illam trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionem ratam Habiturum, nec un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam eandem Impugnaturum. Fructua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam his ita gestis Brevi post ex cancro extinctam fuisse ipsum quoque minoren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem fato functum successorem habuisse fratris fui filium <hi>Andream Fletcher</hi> aduc impuberem. Huic cum per Curatores defuncti lis mota fuisset ad restitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem 13000 marcarum transactione comprehensarum quas illi de suo aiebant ex solutas, succubuisse impuberem in
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:191894:9"/> supremo Scotiae Concessu juridico dene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gata ei quam ex defuncti patrui capite Imploraverat restitutione in integrum adversus transactionem defuncti mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris nomine per Curatores cum fructuaria initam &amp; ab ipso minore defuncto per jus jurandam firmatam. Ab ea vero sententia ad Parliamentum Scoticanum fuisse impuberis nomine ex more Jure{que} concesso appellatum. Nos qui subsig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>navimus in Academia <hi>Lugduno Batava</hi> antecessores <hi>Juridicam</hi> Constituentes <hi>Facultatem</hi> nostram de hac inter Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores &amp; minoris successorem lite men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem exponere responso juridico rogati, duo potissimum arbitrati sumus excuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enda esse primo quidem an ad curatorum officium pertinuerit jus ac potestas transactionem de usu fructu tali pro suo minorenni in eundi; de inde an omne in integrum restitutionis auxilium omne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que aliud juris praesidium minori aut ejus successori prae ripueret interpositum a minore annum decimum &amp; septimum agente jus jurandum transactionis fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandae causa adjectum?</p>
               <p>Primum quod attinet &amp; si jura non in universum omnem Curatoribus trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionem interdicant, sed eam tantum qua jus liquidum Pupilli similiumque remittitur, <hi>L. pignore</hi> 54. <hi>ss: ult: l. inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum</hi> 56. <hi>ss. qui intelam</hi> 4. <hi>D. de furtis. l. prefes</hi> 12. <hi>Cod. de transaction l. Lucius</hi> 46. <hi>ss. ult. D. de adm: &amp; perit. tut. Junct: l. non omne</hi> 16. <hi>Cod: Eod. tit: de Adm: tutor: Tiraquel. lus Ad L: si unquam</hi> 8 <hi>Cod: de revoc. Donat. in verbis donatione largitus num.</hi> 196. <hi>paulus Montanus de tutelis cap.</hi> 33. <hi>num.</hi> 239, 240. <hi>&amp; seqq, &amp; num.</hi> 289, 290, 291. Tamen de hisce demun Casibus sententia haec Admittenda est in quibus litis presentis vel Imminen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis dubius est expectandus eventus, atque adeo in quibus si transactione negotium non componeretur, Judiciali tandem sententia foret inter partes contendentes decidendum; Tunc etenim cum omnino facto hominis decisio sequi debeat &amp; in certa ac ambigua causarum fata sint in certique triumphi satius saepe est verae re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dimendae gratia non nihil de jure pupilli remittere quam experiundo de jure sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mo
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191894:9"/> &amp; extrema tentando pupillum amit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendi totius per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>culo exponere: Unde &amp; hanc in tutoribus transigendi licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam praecipue eo niti fundamento quod honesta Censer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> debeat ac verecunda minime{que} vitu peranda tutorū cogitatio lites execrantium videre est apud Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tanum <hi>d. tract. de tut. cap</hi> 33. <hi>num.</hi> 254. <hi>&amp; seq.</hi> Aliter statuendum ubi nulla lis est vel Metuitur ubi non per judicis senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam incertitudo si quae naegotiis pupilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tibus subsit definienda est, &amp; ab incerta judicis periti imperitive circumspecti aut imprudentis opinione, captu{que} vacillante, lucrum pupilli aut damnū dependet, sed tantum a natura &amp; eventu Conditionis aut diei ex quo suspensa est duratio at{que} interitus rei, determinationem debet ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectate, ubi den que jus pupilli, nulla sui parte Contraversum, sed planum, certumque apparet Quae om<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ia in presenti concurrere facti specie mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festum est: Quippe in qua uti certum erat Minori jus proprietatis in re empta competere, ita è contrario evidens quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>que erat nullum jus usus fructus cum proprietate consolidandi ei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>em aquiren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum fuisse: nisi extincto per usu fructu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ariae mortem usu fructu; &amp; uti nullo probabili Ratione per Judicis sententi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am fructuaria ante obitum potuisset au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferri jus usus fructus ac Pupillo addici, ita nec vice versa spem usus fructus ad pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietatē reversuri potuisse diminui Pupil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo aut interverti; sed omnino ex incerta Mortalitatis eventu, quandoque extituro usus fructus constituti finem pendere.</p>
               <p>Nec est quod regeratur Curatorum hoc unum fuisse propositum ut suo quam maxime consulerent pupillo, paucorum annorum (quinque videlicet &amp; paulo amplius) prestatione presenti jus usus fructus adjiciendo proprietati, a qua il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lud potuisset forte annis integris quadra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginta aut diutius mansisse seperatum; Cum fructuaria transactionis tempore annum agens sextum &amp; quinquagesi mum potuerit naturaliter ad annum Centesimum tanquam finem vitae lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaevi hominis aetatem perducere &amp; à jure fruendi proprietarium minorem impe dire, <hi>L an usus fructus</hi> 56. <hi>D de usu fructu.</hi> Etenim primo quidem illud con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>siderandum,
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191894:10"/> permissum haud esse cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toribus certa suorum pupillorum Como<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da incertis exponere amissionis pericu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lis aut res eorum diminuere lucri majoris incerti obtinendi spe &amp; ita patrimonium diminuendi, causa transigere <hi>D. L.</hi> 46. <hi>ss. ult. D. de Admin. tut.</hi> cui consequens erat nec curatoribus hic competiisse fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultatem faciendi ex substantia pupillari ttedecem Millium marcarum presentem jacturam aut erogationem; ut ex usu fructu sic redempto lucrum sentiret pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pillus post annorum quinque decursum, ubi &amp; sine ulla numeratione potuisset Anno primo usus fructus finire, uti id e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam in hac facti specie contigisse asseri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur. Quamvis enim haud sit eundum inficias, quin quandoque boni ac provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di patres familias medico praesenti soluto proprietati suae adjiciant usum fructum penes alterum existentē, qui redemptio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne praetermissa diutius potuisset a propri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etate manere segregatus; non tamen quic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quid diligens pater familias liberrimus rerum suarum moderator ac arbiter spe lucri majoris tentat, quicquid periculo amissionis non imprudenter exponat, cum emolumenti captandi voto, id etiam Curatoribus aliisque similibus rerum a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lienarum administratoribus non liberum arbitrium, sed administrandi tantum po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testatem habentibus, videre debet con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessum esse. <hi>Non omni titulo res Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilli alienandi potestatem Tutores ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bent, sed administrationis tantum cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sa distrahentes quae iis veuundare licet justam causam possidendi comparanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus prestat,</hi> pro regula traditum est ab <hi>Impp: in L. non omni.</hi> 16. <hi>Cod: de Ad. Tut.</hi> Et certe ista si Tutoribus ac Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoribus permittenda fuerint occasio facilis erit, ac via declivis qua Minores ad paupertatem festinent. Mercaturam exercere &amp; ea ratione ad opulentiam grassare, Dominis permissum est; nec tamen ideo recte aut ex officii prescripto Tutor fecerit, si bene collocatos faenori nummos Pupillares, aut etiam otiosos, maturius ditescendi causa negotiationi instituendae impenderit unius forte naufragii calamitate in totum perituros hinc in <hi>L. qui negotiationem</hi> 58. <hi>D. de Ad, &amp; per. Tut.</hi> cum pater Pupilli per du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>os
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191894:10"/> libertos suos mercaturam exercuisset nominatim Testamento suo caven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um censuit. Et Libertis hisce impuberi fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio Tutoribus datis injungendum ut ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotium eodem modo exerceretur quo se vivo exercebatur. Cumque alter Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor redactum ex ista negotiatione lucrum sibi cuperit reservatum, &amp; pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niae Pupillaris usuras inferendo defungi vellet, Responsum fuit eum debere Rationes reddere secundum defuncti vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luntatem adeoque lucrum omne Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiationis ac damnum Pupillo impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate. Cui consequens erit ipsum Libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>randum fuisse sola usuarum prestatione &amp; suo periculo fuisse negotiaturum si non nominatim Pupilli Pater Testamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to suo negotiationis praecipisset continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ationem. Unde &amp; interpretes merito Colligerent tutorem non posse mercatu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, a defuncto Pupilli Patre non exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citam, Pupilli nomine &amp; periculo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ercere, &amp; si Pater exercuerit non alio modo quam quo is egerat continuare; uti post <hi>Alexandrum vol.</hi> 5. <hi>consiil.</hi> 132 <hi>num.</hi> 14. &amp; Marquardum de Mercatura <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 9 <hi>num.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; seq.</hi> Notat Bru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem annusad <hi>dict. L,</hi> 58. <hi>de ad tut num.</hi> 3. Mercium quoque transvehendarum pe riculum lege ac consuetudine probante. In se recipiunt non pauci Patres familias Industrii accepto presenti periculipretio; nec tamen Jure quisquam hanc curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus asseruerit potestatem ut Pupillo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum suorum nomine ac periculo rerum trajectitiarum promitterent securitatem, seu (ut loquuntur) facerent assecuratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem. Nec ignotum, licitas esse de he<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reditatibus ex fidei commisso post mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem fiduciarii restituendis transactiones, ut vel fiduciarius statim ipse vivus resti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuat, retenta hereditatis parte, vel fidei commissarius presente modico accepto contentus ulteriori renuntiet spei. <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>Cod. de pactis l. cum proponas</hi> 16 <hi>Cod. de pactis l. de fidei commiss.</hi> 11. <hi>Cod. de transact.</hi> Iniquum tamen sore; si haec transigendi Species arbitrio nudo Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum nullo Magistratus decreto &amp; cog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitione inter veniente relinqueretur, in aperto est. Reditus denique vitalitios emere haud insolitum illis qui rerum suarum satagunt: ex quo emtionis gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>re
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191894:11"/> licet Pupillis ad aetatem provexiorem per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venturis non leve lucrū accedere possit, quia tamen sors ipsa Pupillo brevi post moriente, possit perire, potestatis sui terminos Curator accesserit si Pupilla<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rem pecuniam in Redituum talium ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quisitionem Pupilli periculo voluerit erogatam. Adeo ut nunc apud Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landos (ubi redituum talium vitalitiorum frequentissimus usus est) <hi>anno</hi> 1671. 3 <hi>Octob:</hi> urgentibus utilitatibus fisci, tunc unde quaque pecuniis conquirentis, per Hollandiae ordines cautum suerit tutores &amp; Curatores extra cavillationis aut re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehentionis metū posse pupillorū pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niis &amp; periculo ac commodo tales abaera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rio reditus comparare sed tamen non ali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter quam praecedente curiae provincialis vel Magistratus decreto. Et quamvis Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landorum juribus exteros non ligari ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peditum sit, rationabilem tamen &amp; li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitatum ex aequo tutorum potestatem etiam ex aliarum gentium moratiorum usibus confirmari absonum non est. At, quid, obfecro, interest, reditum vita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litium quis pupillo comparet &amp; sortem perdat, an presenti 13000. Mercarum pretio incertam redimat usus fructus itidem a mortalitate dependentis, dura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem?</p>
               <p>Accedit hisce quod in casu proposito usus fructus ipse; si à proprietate diutius mansisset separatus nullo tamen modo damnosus aut onerosus esse potuisset Pupillo: Quippe penes quem durante usus fructus jure tanta pretii quantitas vi pacti expressi residua debeat esse, ut ex usuris ejus usufructuariae quotannis sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfieri potuerat: Sic ut nulla satis justa aut urgens transigendi ratio vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deri possit subfuisse. Etiamsi enim per Curatores allegatum sit non nisi decem millia ex millibus quadraginta duobus, retentis fuisse Transactionis tempore residua; cum tamen id non appareat, nec dum redditis tutelae Rationibus, &amp; si maxime pateret, ratiocinia supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riora nequaquam subvertaret, inducti omnino sumus, ut existimemus Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores in presenti facti specie de usu fructu transigentis, solutis tredecem mercarum millibus, absque ulla precedente Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistratus cognitione ac decreto egressus
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191894:11"/> potestatis Curatoriae limites, &amp; ea egisse quae ad Curatoris officium ac administrationem non pertinebant: at{que} adeo transactionem illam ut ipso jure nullam; nullum potuisse pupillo prejudicium inferre.</p>
               <p>Sed &amp; si summo jure hoc transactionis genus Curatoribus permissum esse statueretur (ut cumque contrarium abunde ad structum sit) Non tamen propterea deneganda minori foret adversus laesionem ex hac transactione illatam restitutio; Cum sat magna imo supina negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentia (dolum enim si non manifeste probetur sive testibus sive juris jurandi remedio, in Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratoribus familiae splendore Generosis presu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere fas non est) in ea Caelebranda videatur Commissa, quod scilicet non diligentius in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditionem &amp; valetudinem fructuariae cum qua transigendum erat inquisiverint. Cum enim Mortalitas ex probabilibus aetatis, debilitatis, morbi, aliis{que} Circumstantis, Serius otiusve fructuariae superventura unicum fuerit trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionis interponendi fundamentum, necesse omnino fuit, ut curiosa plane in corporis habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum ac valetudinem fructuariae inquisitio ad hiberetur, quae si intercessisset, etiam Cancri scientia &amp; inde mortis pro pediem imminentis suspitio potuisset ad curatores aeque ac ad alios pervenisse, nec bona fides fuisset dein passa ut ad hujusmodi transactionem Certiorati pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessissent cum tam manifesta pecuniae pupilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris jactura. Dum ergo in eo indagando negli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentes fuerint negare nequit quin ex lata eo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum culpa in hoc 13000 marcarum damnum Minor inciderit. Minoribus vero ita laesis per in integrum restitutionem solere succurri juris ideo triti ac certi est ut probatione haud opus sit.</p>
               <p>Alteram ex jure jurando minoris ad trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionem firmandam interposito, natam con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traversiam
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191894:12"/> ac difficultatem ut enodemus; in antecessum praemittendum existimamus, ita de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mum de jure Romano Sacramenta puberum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>violabiter fuisse custodienda ex vulgata <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; Anthens. Sacram. puber. Cod. si adversus vendit.</hi> si de caetero omnia legittime Gesta fuissent ex legū prescripto, sic ut summo jure rata ac firma fuerint nec alia quam ex capite laesionis per Minorennitatem Contingentis restitutio in in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrum adversus ea fuisset metuenda; Cum alioquin non ex prescripto legum per minores contracta atque adeo nulla ni restitutionis qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem auxilio indiguerint uti id ex <hi>L. quidem</hi> 11. <hi>Cod. de prediis &amp; aliis reb. minor.</hi> 25. <hi>annis.</hi> Abunde colligitur dum re scriptum fuit decreto non in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terposito de prediis minorum Alienandis super vacuum esse de vili praetio rei distractae tractare Cum senatus consulti autoritas retento Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nio alienandi viā obstruxerit; interposito vero decreto, &amp; ita jureperfecto venditione restitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nē adversus viliori praetio factam distractionē potuisse impetrari. At si jus jurandum mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris in super accessisset, Tum demum verum fuit restitutionis remedium fuisse denegatum per dict. <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>Cod. si adversus vendit.</hi> ita sentienti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nobiscum Donello <hi>Commentar. Jur. Civil. l.</hi> 21. <hi>cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Zousio ad pandect. Tit. de minor</hi> 25. <hi>annis Num</hi> 40: <hi>Peresio ad tit. Cod. si adversis ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit. Num.</hi> 1.2. Quamvis enim pluribus arrisit Martini opinio etiam invalidos minorum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus jure jurando validos &amp; firmos effici contendentis quos longa serie recenset, <hi>Joh. a sand de prohibita, alien<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="5 letters">
                        <desc>•••••</desc>
                     </gap>e cap.</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 94. Bulgari tamen ad sola negotia summo jure valida <hi>D. L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; D. authenti{que}</hi> restringentis sententiam saniori Romani juris prudentiae rationi conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niri arbitramur, Nam cum ea quae per majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rennes quoscunque contra leges gesta sunt sic ipso jure nulla sint ut nec jus jurandum eis firmitatem adere queat <hi>L. non dubium</hi> 5. <hi>Cod. de Leg. L. juris Gentium</hi> 7. §. <hi>&amp; Generaliter</hi> 16. <hi>de pactis:</hi> Necesse est ut absurditatis evitandae Causa longe magis infirma manere dicamus per minorem contra leges gesta, utcunque juris jurandi Religione firmata nisi deteriorem minorennium vellemus esse conditionem in contrahendo quam majorennium contra mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festum minoris aetatis favorem.</p>
               <p>Haec si presenti accomodentur negotio aper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum erit, jus jurandum a minore transactionis firmandi causa interpositum minore non posse aut debere effectu inspecto damnosum esse. Sive enim transactionem ipso jure nullum con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipiamus, tanquam ad curatoris officium haud pertinentem, &amp; sine Magistratus decreto factam, non potuit actus ille ipso jure invalidus ex ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessorio jure jurando per minorem prestito ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum accipere firmitatem. Sin ex adverso trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actionem summo jure substitisse quis contendat (licet contra rationes juris ante propositas) ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men cum laesio minoris ex manifesta ac magna curatorum negligentia appareat jusjurandum
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191894:12"/> minoris impedire nequit extraordinarium re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitutionis adjutorium, huic aetate laesae solitum indulgeri; eo quod evidenti laborat defectu ac ipso jure nullum est. Quemadmodum enim in aliis quibuscunque minorum Curatores ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bentium Conventionibus necessaria omnino est Curatorū autoritas ea{que} deficienteinutile prorsus est quicquid gestum fuerit, nec alio habendum loco quam quo contracta per eos quibus curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ri per praetorem dato bonis inter dictum est. <hi>L. si Curatorem</hi> 3. <hi>Cod, de in integrum restit: Minor.</hi> ita quoque irritum ipso jure Censeri debet jus jurandum illud promissorium quo minor se contra contractus interpositi fidem non ventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum policetur, si Curatoris autoritas deficiat. Licet autem presenti in negotio primo fronte videri possit Curatorum autoritatem haud de fuisse dum hi ipsi minorem ad juris jurandi re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligionem exhortati sunt ac induxerunt; per pensis tamen penitius rei gestae circumstantiis in notescet facile ipso jure nullam fuisse hanc cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum autoritatem. si modo conferre libuerit vulgatam juris Regulam quae tutores ac cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tores in rem suam propriam, propriam{que} utili tatem autores fieri diserte vetat, ac tali casu Curatores ad istum actū specialiter constituendi Consensum requirit <hi>L.</hi> 1. <hi>D. de autor. Tut</hi> §. <hi>ult. Insti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ut. eod. tit.</hi> Etenim tran<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>actio de usu fructu plenissimam esset adepta securitatem ac firmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem in commodum fructuariae quae Curato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res opulentas satis, ad implementum transactio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nis proprio nomine sibi reddiderat devinctos, &amp; inde efficaciter convenire poterat, utcun{que} alioquin transactio in se spectata omni fuisset firmitate destituta, <hi>Arg. L. &amp; si is.</hi> 9. <hi>Cod. de prediis &amp; aliis rev. minor. sine decret. non alienand.</hi> Super vacaneum prorsus fuit quantum quidem ad fructuariam attinet, hoc subsecutum mino<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ris sacramentum; ac proinde concipi non potest in alterius cujusquam quam curatorum ipsorum utilitatem securitatem{que} excogita tum acpresti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stitum, scilicet, ut vel ipsi liberarentur ab actione, tutelae, per pupillum postea adversus se ob damnosam transactionem &amp; dissipatam sine necessitate uel utilitate pecuniam pupilla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rem movendae, vel ne ipsi ex suo intercessione apud fructuariam facta conventi ac solventes in damno harerent. Si ipsis quantitatem tre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decem millium Mercarum postea repetentibus aut in pupilli Rationes Imputantibus, nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatem transactionis minor opositurus fuisset vel saltem extraordinarium adversus damnosam transactionem auxilium imploraturus At quid quaeso est in rem suam Curatores autores fieri, si haec non est, ubi omni modo sibi securitatem &amp; ab actione tutelae lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rationem ex minoris Sacramento, autoritate sua &amp; hortatu prestito tentarunt obtinere.</p>
               <p>Quibus omnibus tandem ex abundanti adji<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciendum est <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; auth Sacramentum puberum Cod, si adversus vendit;</hi> ita communi Gentium usu esse abolitam testantibus illud hispanis,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191894:13"/> Italis, Gallis, Belgis, aliisque juris interpreti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus ac pragmaticis ut quaeri merito possit, in qua orbis parte aut quo in angulo reservatis e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam num fuerit hujus l. &amp; Authen: usus &amp; hoc quidem urgentissima ratione cum experientia docuisset eodem aetatis lubrico eademque facili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate qua ad contrahendum in Substantiae suae pernitiem inducuntur Minores, etiam ad con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractus suos jure Jurando muniendos instigari &amp; permoveri ac multa minorum Patrimonia exhausta fuisse prae textu Sacramenti quod per in fidias artesque non bonas aetate fragili judicii imbecilitate laborante contrahentium captiosa extorserat avaritia &amp; per fas nefasque lucrandi cupido <hi>Christineus vol.</hi> 5. <hi>decis.</hi> 225 <hi>num.</hi> 20. <hi>&amp; seq. Pinellus ad l</hi> 2. <hi>Cod. ae rescind. rendit. part</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 11. <hi>Argentreus, ad consuetudine</hi> Brittan. <hi>Art.</hi> 471. <hi>num.</hi> 1. 2. <hi>Gudelinus, de jure novis. l.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 14. <hi>vers. non immorabor Hen. Kinshot Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sponso</hi> 102. <hi>num.</hi> 18. <hi>Bugneon de l. Abrogat l.</hi> 1. <hi>Satyra</hi> 119. <hi>Peresius Tit. Cod si adversus vendit. num. ult.</hi> Aliique quos referr Groenewgn. <hi>de leg. Abrogat. ad</hi> D. <hi>ut si adversus vendit.</hi> &amp; Christineus in notis ad Bugnion. D. <hi>loco.</hi> At{que} hinc ipsis quo{que} frisiis licet alioquin religiosissimis Romani juris cultoribus &amp; asseclis in tantum D l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; Authen, displicuit dispositio, ut san citum ab iis fuerit re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nunciationes ac Contractus Minorū juratas non plus operari quā in juratas simul{que} prohibitum, ne tabellionis jure jurando subjecerent contrac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus minorū, vel ab ipsis exigerent Sacramenta sub paena amissionis officii &amp; alia Arbitraria, Statuta Frizii. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 7. §. 5. <hi>Job. a sand.</hi> D. <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibit, aliena Cap.</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 97. in quam sere sen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentiam etiam Parliamentū. Scotiae anno. 1681. statutum. Concepisse Suggestum nobis est.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>Propter quae omnia nulli dubitamus quin Minor adversus hanc Transactionem juratam, de qua lis est, succurendum sit, ne ullam inde Laesionem sustineat, atque ita juris esse, secun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum animi norstri Religionem censemus, in quorum fidem hisce subscripsimus, ac Minore Accademiae Sigillo Responsum Munivimus: Lugduni in Batavis <date>die 7. May 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
                  <signed>
                     <hi>Sic Subtr.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>Pr. Vitriarius J. C. t9. Pt. Acad. Rect.</item>
                        <item>Johannes Voet.</item>
                        <item>Anton. Matthaeus,</item>
                        <item>
                           <hi>Loci Sigilli</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Gerardus Noodd.</item>
                     </list>
                  </signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:191894:8"/>
            <div xml:lang="eng" type="verdict">
               <head>The State of the Affair.</head>
               <p>SEeing this hath appeared to be the matter of Fact, from the shewed Copies of the <hi>Scotish</hi> Registers translated into Latine, that Sir <hi>Andrew Fletcher</hi> at a certain rate purchased to himself the Lands <hi>Aberlady's:</hi> But because of a Liferent Annuity in these Lands of <hi>Jean Seatoun</hi> Spouse unto <hi>Kenuedy</hi> of <hi>Ardmillan;</hi> It was agreed upon by the express Paction between the Seller and Buyer, that while the Liferent continued, the sum of 42000 Me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ks of the Prom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>sed price should remain in the hands of the Buyer, that from the yearly Interest of that Money (according to the custom of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey) amounting to 2500 Merks, the quantity of so many Merks might be se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cured due, and to be payed yearly to the Liferentrix according to her Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Right. The Buyer having Decea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sed and left a Son Minor, <hi>Archbald Fletcher,</hi> his Curators the Laird of <hi>Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barrony,</hi> and the other Curators Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acted with the Lady's Liferentrix going into the fifty six year of her Age, and then Diseased with a Cancer; that she for thirteen thousand Merks should quite her Liferent R ght to the Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor being Minor; and so should renounce all Right of Servitude. But for Security of this Transaction, the Curators be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came Caution, and bound their own Person; and moreover perswaded their Pupil that he being but Sixteen years of Age, should promise by a Solemn Oath to ratify that Transaction, and never to quarrel or Impugne it, that these things being so done within a short time after the Liferentrix Dyed, of the said Cancer, that the Minor himself also hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Dyed, had a Successor his Brothers Son <hi>Andrew Fletcher,</hi> as yet an Infant.</p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:191894:9"/>
               <p>And the Curators of the Desunct having intented an Action against him, for Restitution of the thirteen Thousand Merks comprehended in the Transacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which they pretended were payed out of their own Money, that the said <hi>Aberlady</hi> was overcome in the Action: In the Supreme Court of Justice of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> Restitution in Integrum being denyed to him which he had implored on the head of his Deceast Fathers Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, against the Transaction made by the Curators with the Liferentrix in name of the Deceast Minor and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by the Defunct Minor himself by an Oath. And that an Appeal had been made from that Sentence to the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland</hi> in the name of the Child, according to the Custom and Right granted. We Subscribers, Doctors and Professors of Law in the Universi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of <hi>Leiden,</hi> constituting the Faculty of Law, being desired, to declare our Opinion in Law anent this Plea between the Curators, and Successor of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor; have judged that two things espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially are to be inquired into first. Whither a Right and power of making a Transaction about such, a Liferent for their Minor belonged to the Office of Curators. Next whether the Oath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven by the Minor going in the Seven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen year of his Age, added for confirm<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ation of the Transaction took away from the Minor or his Successor all help of Restitution <hi>in integrum</hi> and all other aid of the Law.</p>
               <p>As to the first, Albeit the Law doth not Discharge Curators altogether from all Transactions, but that only whereby the clear Right of the Pupil and the like is remitted <hi>l pignore</hi> 54 <hi>ss. ult. l. inter. dum</hi> 56. <hi>ss. qui tutelam</hi> 4. <hi>D. de furtis. l. praeses</hi> 12. <hi>Cod. de Transaction: l: Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cius,</hi> 46: <hi>ss. ult: D. administrat. &amp; peric: tutor. iuuct. l. non omni</hi> 16 <hi>Cod, eod, tit. de adminictrat. tutor.</hi> Tyraquellus <hi>ad l. si unquam.</hi> 8. <hi>Cod. de revocand. do. uation. in verbis donatione largitus. num.</hi> 196 <hi>Paulus Montanus de tutelis Cap.</hi> 33. <hi>num.</hi> 239. 240 <hi>&amp; seqq. &amp; num</hi> 289. 290. 291. Nevertheless this O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion is only to be admitted concerning
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:191894:9"/> these Cases, in which doubtful event is to be expected of the present approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or iminent Plea; and so in which if the Business should not be agreed by a Transaction, it would come at last to be decided by a Judicial sentence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Parties contending, for then seeing the decision ought to follow al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together by the Judgement of a man, and the Destinies of Causes are uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain and doubtful and Triumphs uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, it is ofttimes better for preserving of that which is ones Right to remit some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of the Right of the Pupil, then by making a Tryal of the <hi>summum jus,</hi> and experimenting Extremities to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pose the Pupil to the Hazard of loosing all: And even this power of Transact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing allowed to Curators especially lean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on that Foundation, that the thought of Tutors abhor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ing Pleas ought to be judged Honest, and Modest, and not at all to be blamed, as is to be seen in <hi>Montanus.</hi> D. <hi>tract. de tutelis, Cap.</hi> 33 <hi>num.</hi> 254. <hi>&amp; seqq.</hi> It is to be judged otherwayes, where there is, or is fear<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ed no Plea, where uncertainty (if there be any in the Pupils Business) is not to be determined by the Sentence of a Judge, and the gain or loss of a Pupil dependeth not on the uncertain Opinion and wavering Capacity of a skilful or un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sk<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lful, Circumspect or imprudent Judge, but only ought to be determined from the nature and event of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition or day, from which the Durati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or ruine of the thing dependeth; Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally where it appeareth that the Right of the Pupil is controverted in no part of it self, but is plain, clear and certain All which do manifestly concurr in this Case: Because in this Case as it was certain, that the Minor had a Right of Property in the Estate Bought, so on the contrair it was also evident, that no Right of the Liferent to be joined and consol<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>dat with the Property was to be purchased by him, unless the Liferent had been extinct by the Death of the Liferentrix: And as with no probable Reason could the Right of the Liferent have been taken away from the Liferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix before her Death, and granted to
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:191894:10"/> the Pupil by the sentence of Judge, so again neither could the hope of the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent about to return to the Property have been diminished to the Pupil or convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed away: But that the end of the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed Liferent altogether dependeth on the event of uncertain Mortality at some time to happen.</p>
               <p>Nor is there any ground to Reply, that this was the only purpose of the Cura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors, that they might provide for the good of their Pupil as much as was pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible, with the present payment of a few Years Annuity (to wit, of five and a little more) by adding the right of Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to the property, from which per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps it might have remained separate fourty whole Years, or longer: Seeing the Liferentrix at the time of the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action going in the fifty and sixth Year of her age, might have naturally pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longed her Life to an Hundred Years, as to the end of the Life of a long living Man, and have hindred the Proprietar Minor from the Right of Enjoying. L. An. usus fructus 56. D de usu fructu.</p>
               <p>For first indeed it is to be considered, That it is not permitted to Curators to expose the certain Advantages of their Pupils to the uncertain hazards of Lose<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or to diminish their Goods in hope of obtaining a greater uncertain Gain; and so to Transact to diminish their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>state. D. L. 46. <hi>ss</hi> ult. D. de admin. Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor. To which it was consequential, that neither had the Curators here a power of making the present loss, or bestowing of thirteen Thousand Merks out of the Pupil's substance, that from the Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent so bought the Pupil might find gain after the running out of five Years; where even without any payment of ready Money, the Liferent might have ended the first Year; as that also is said to have hapened in this Matter of Fact: For although it is not to be denied, but that sometimes good and provident Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prietars, having payed a little ready Money, may add to their own property a Liferent be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ng in the power of another which if the purchase had been neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, might have continued longer sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the property: Nevertheless,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:191894:10"/> whatsoever a diligent Proprietar, who is a most free Manager and Judge of his own Goods, tryeth in hope of grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Gain, whatsoever he not imprudent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly exposeth to the hazard of Lossing with a desire of receiving Advantage,, that ought not to be granted also to Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators and other the like Administrators of other Mens Affairs: <hi>Who have not an absolute power, but only a liberty of managing, Tutors having not a power of alienating the Goods of their Pupill upon every pretence, but selling only for management what they have liberty to sell they warr and to the Purchasers a just Cause of possessing, is a Rule given by the Emperors in L non omvi.</hi> 16 <hi>Cod: de administr: Tut.</hi> And surely, if these things were to be permitted to Tutors and Curators they would give an easie occasion and ready way of hastning Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors to poverty. It is permitted to Ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners to Merchandize, and by that means to strive to come to Wealth: Never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theless, a Tutor shall not do rightly, or according to the prescript of his Office, if to become the sooner Rich he should bestow on Trading his Pupils Money that are well given out upon Interest, or are even lying idle, which perhaps may wholly perish by one Shipwrack. Hence in <hi>L. quì negotiationem</hi> 58 <hi>D. de Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nistr. &amp; peric. Tutor.</hi> When the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of a Pupil had excercised Merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dize by two of his freed Men, he judged it was to be expresly cautioned in his Testament, and to be particularly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned to these freed Men given as Tu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors to his Son a Child, that his Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandize should be managed in the same manner as it was managed while he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self was alive: And when the one of the Tutors desired the Gain made by that Traffiquing to be reserved to himself, and would discharge himself by giving the Interest of his Pupil's Money, an O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion was given in Law that he ought to make his accounts according to the Will of the Dead, and so impute to the Pupil all the Gain and Damnage of the Traffique. To which it was consequent, that he was to be freed by the paying of the Interest alone, and was to Trade at
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:191894:11"/> his own hazard, if the the Pupil's Father had not expresly in his Testament com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the continuation of Traffiquing. Whence also Interpreters have deserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gathered, That a Tutor cannot in the Name and to the Hazard of the Pupil exercise Merchandize not exercised by the defunct Father of the Pupil, and if the Father have exercised it, to continue it in no other manner than he had done, as after <hi>Alexander Vol.</hi> 5. <hi>Consil.</hi> 132. <hi>num:</hi> 14. <hi>Et</hi> Marquard <hi>de Mercatura. lib:</hi> 1. <hi>cap:</hi> 9. <hi>num.</hi> 5. <hi>&amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>eqq,</hi> marketh <hi>Brunemannus ad D. l.</hi> 58. <hi>de admin: tut: num:</hi> 3. Many industrious Proprie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ving before them the present pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect of the danger, undertake the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard of Transporting Wares, with the Approbation of Law and Custom, yet no Man will justly assert this power to Curators, that in the Name and to the Hazard of their Pupils they might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mise Security of the things Transported, or (as they say) might insure them. Nor is it unknown that Transactions are lawful, about Inheritances of Trust to be restored after the Death of the Tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sty, that either the Trusty himself be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing alive may restore, having retained a great part of the Inheritance, or the Trusty presently being content with the present little received may quite further hope L. 1. <hi>Cod: de pactis: l. cum proponas</hi> 16 <hi>Cod: de pactis l. de fidei commisso.</hi> 11. <hi>Cod: de Transaction:</hi> Nevertheless, it is plain that it would be unjust, if this sort of Transacting should be left to the bare pleasure of the Curators, no De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creet, Act, and Cognizance of a Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gistrate interveening. Finally, it is not unusual to those who go diligently about their Affairs to buy Liferents. From which kind of Buying, although no small Gain might come to the Pupils, that are to arise to a more advanced Age: Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless, because the stock it self might perish, the Pupil dying shortly after, the Curator would go beyond the bounds of his power. if he would bestow the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils Money on the purchasing of such Rents. So that now among the <hi>Hollan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders</hi> (where there is very frequent use of such Liferents) in the Year 1671
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:191894:11"/>
                  <hi>October</hi> 3. the Necessity of the Exchequer then calling for Money from whence soever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing pressing, it was enacted by the States of <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> that Tutors and Curators without fear of Cavillation or Reprehension might purchase such Rents from the Treasury with their Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pils Money, and to their Peril or Advantage, but yet no otherwayes than that a Decreet of the Court of the Province or Magistrate shovld preceed: And albeit it be soon Answe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that Strangers are not bound by the Laws of the <hi>Hollanders;</hi> yet it is not absurd, that the power of Tutors being reasonable and li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited by Equity be also confirmed by the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of other Nations that have better Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stoms than ordinary. But what difference is there I pray you, whether one purchase a Liferent to a Pupil, and loss the Stock, or at the present Rate of thirteen thousand Merks he redeem the uncertain continuance of a Life<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Annuity, depending likewayes on the mortality of the person.</p>
               <p>To these it is added, that in the Case pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed the Liferent Annuity it self, if it had continued longer separate from the propriety; yet it could have no way been hurtful or bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>densome to the Pupil, because in whose hand, while the Liferent right continued, so great a quantity of the price should be remaining by vertue of the express paction, that satisfaction might be made thereby to the Liferentrix out of the Interest of it: So that there may seem to have been no just enough or pressing Reason of transacting. For although it be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Curators, that there were not remaining but ten thousand of the fourty two thousand retained at the time of the Transa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction; nevertheless, seeing that doth not ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, the Tutors Accounts not being as yet made, it could not at all subvert the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Reasonings, albeit it could appear never so much, we have been altogether induced to think that the Curators in the present Matter of Fact transacting about the Lifrentrix Annuity, having payed thirteen thousand Merks, without any precedent Cognizance and Decreet of a Magistrate went beyond the bounds of the power of Curators, and did those things which did not belong to the Offiee and Management of a Curator: And so that that Transaction null in Law it self, could bring no prejudice to the Pupil.</p>
               <p>But although in rigour of Law this kind of Transaction should be determined to be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to Curators (howsoever the contrary hath been abundantly proved) nevertheless Restitution should not therefore be denied to the Minor aguinst the harm and laesion done him by this Transaction; seing great enough yea supine Negligenee, (for it is not lawful to presume deceit in Curators generous by the honour of their Families, if it be not mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>festly proven either by Witnesses or the Remedy of an Oath) may seem to have been commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in celebrating it, to wit, that they did not more diligently enquire into the Condition and Health of the Liferentrix, with whom the Transaction was to be made: For seeing Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality about to come sooner or latter to the Liferentrix, from the probable Circumstances of Age, Weakness, Disease and others, was the only foundation of interposing the Transaction it was oltogether necessary that a curious Inquisition should be made into the Constitution and Health of the Liferentrix Body. Which if it had interceeded, the knowledge also of the Cancer, and from thence the suspicion of Death shorty approaching might have come to the Curators as well as to others: Nor had good Fidelity then suffered them certified to proceed to such a Transaction, with so manifest a loss of the Pupil's Money.</p>
               <p>Seing therefore they were negligent in searching out that; it cannot be denied, but
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:191894:12"/> that by their great fault the Minor fell into this loss of thirteen thousand Merks: But that Minors so wronged used to be succoured by Restitution <hi>in integrum,</hi> is so ordinary and certain in Law that it needeth no probation.</p>
               <p>That we may open up the other Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versie and Difficultie arising from the Oath of the Minor interposed to confirm the Trans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>action, we think It is before hand to be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mised, that by the Roman Law the Oaths of Lads grown up, were to have been inviola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly keeped <hi>ex vulgata L.</hi> 1. <hi>&amp; authent. sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menta puberum Cod. si adversus vendition.</hi> if as to the rest all things had been done legally accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the prescript of the Laws; so that they had been ratified and firm in rigour of Law, neither had any other intire Restitution against them to have been feared, than from the head of Laesion happening by Minority. When o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wayes not being contracted by Minors according to the prescript of the Laws and so Null, they needed not so much as the aid of Restitution: As <hi>ex L. siquidem</hi> 11 <hi>Cod. de prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus &amp; aliis rebus Minor. Sine Decret. non alien. &amp; L. pen. D. de Minor.</hi> 25. <hi>anuis,</hi> is abundant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gathered; while a prescript was given, that it was superfluous to treat of the cheap Rate of an Estate sold, a Decreet not being inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed about alienating the Lands of Minors, seing the authority of an Act of the Senat hindred the alienating, and retained the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion. But a Decreet being interposed, and the Vendition so perfited by Law, Restitution might have been obtained against Sale made at a cheaper Rate. But if the Oath of a Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor had moreover been added, then at length it was true, that the Remedy of Restitution was denied. <hi>Per D. L.</hi> 1. <hi>Cod. si adversus vendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem:</hi> So judging with us <hi>Donellus Coment. jur. Civill. libr.</hi> 21. <hi>Cap.</hi> 13. <hi>Zoesius ad pandect. tit. de Minorib.</hi> 25. <hi>aunis. num.</hi> 40. <hi>Perezius ad tit: Cod. si adversus vendit num.</hi> 1, 2. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the Opinion of <hi>Martinus</hi> hath pleased many, contending that even the invalide Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts of Minors are made valide and firm by an Oath, who are reckoned over by <hi>John</hi> à <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de de prohibita alienatione Cap:</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 94. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheless we judge that the Opinion of <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garus</hi> restricting <hi>D. L. primam &amp; D. authenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cam</hi> to Businesses alone valide in rigour of Law agreeth to the sounder reason of Roman <hi>Juris prudens:</hi> For, seing these things, which have been done by whatsoever Majors against the Laws, being so Null in Law it self, that nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther can an Oath add firmness to them. <hi>L. non dubium.</hi> 5. <hi>Cod, de legibus. L. juris gentium</hi> 7. <hi>ss. &amp; gereraliter.</hi> 16. <hi>D. de pactis.</hi> It is necessary that to shun Absurdity we say, that things done by a Minor against the Laws do remain far more infirm, howsoever confirmed by the Religion or Tye of an Oath, unless we would have the condition of Minors in contracting to be
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:191894:12"/> worse than that of Majors against the manifest favour of a Minors Age.</p>
               <p>If these things be applyed to the present Business, it will be clear that an Oath inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed by a Minor to confirm a Transaction, neither can or ought to be hurtfull to a Minor the effect being looked to. For whether we conceave the Transaction null in Law it self, as not belonging to the Office of a Curator, and made without the Decreet of a Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strate, that Act invalid in Law it self could not receive any firmness from an accessory Oath given by a Minor. But if on the contrary any contend that the Trunsaction subsisted in Rigour of Law) although against the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons of Law formerly proposed) nevertheless, seeing the Laesion of the Minor appeareth from the manifest and great neglect of the Curators, the Oath of the Minor cannot hinder the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary help of Restitution, usually indulg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to this Age being lae<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed and wronged, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cause it laboureth with an evident defect, and is null in Law it self. For even as in other whatsoever Agreements of Minors having Curators, the Authority of the Curators is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>together necessary to the Agreements; and it being wanting whatsoever hath been done is altogether unprofitable, and to be esteemed in no other place, then Contracts by them, who are interdicted from their Goods a Curator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing given them by the pretor. <hi>l. si Curatorem</hi> 3 <hi>de Cod. de in intergrum restit Minorum.</hi> So also that promissory Oath ought to be judged void and of no effect in Law it self, whereby the Minor promiseth that he will not come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst or oppose the Faith of the interposed Contract, if the Aunhority of a Curator be wanting. For although in the present Busi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness it might seem at first View, that the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of Curators had not been wanting, while they themselves exhorted and induced the Minor to the Religious tye of an Oath: Nevertheless having more throughly consider- the Circumstances of the thing done, it will easily appear, that this Authority of the Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rators was null in Law it self, if any please to compare the common Rule of Law, which ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>presly forbiddeth Tutors and Curators to be Authors and Advisers to their own proper inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rest and proper profit, and in that case requireth the consent of a Curator specially to be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed to that Act <hi>l.</hi> 1. D. <hi>de Autorit. tutor. ss. ult. justit eod. tit.</hi> For seeing the Transaction about the Liferent had got very full security and firmness for the Advantage of the Liferen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trix, who had Curators Rich enough for the implement of that Transaction in their own name oblidged to her self, who from that might have been effectually pursued, howso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever otherwayes the Transaction considered in it self had been destitute of all firmness; <hi>Arg. l. etsi is</hi> 9. <hi>Cod. de praediis &amp; aliis rebus Minor, sine
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:191894:13"/> decreto non aliend.</hi> This Oath of the Minor having followed was altogether superfluous indeed as ro what concerns the Liferentrix, and therefore it cannot be conceived to have been contrived and given for the profit and security of any other, than the Curators them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves; to wit that either they themselves might be freed from an Action of tutelage, that would be afterwards raised by the Pupill against themselves for the hurtful Transaction and the Pupils Money squandered away without ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cessity or profite; or lest they themselves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing conveened upon their Obligation made with the Liferentrix, and paying should bear the loss, if the Minor had been to oppose the nullity of the Transaction to them afterwards seeking back the quantity of Thirteen thousand Merks or at least had been to implore extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary aid against the hurtful Transaction. But what pray you, is it for Curators to be Authors for their own interest, if this be not it, whereby their own Authority and Exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made, they have tryed by all means to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain security to themselves and freedom from the Action of tutelage by the Oath of the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor.</p>
               <p>To all which it is at last to be added over and above out of abundance that the Law and <hi>Auth. Sacramenta puberum Cod. si ad versus venditionem;</hi> are so abolished by the common use and practice of Nations, as the <hi>Spanish, Italian, French, Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gick,</hi> and other interpeters and Practitioners in the Law bear witness, that it might deserved<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be asked in what part of the World, or in what Corner hath the use of this Law and Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thentick been reserved. And this indeed for a very pressing Reason; when Experience had taught that with the same inconstancy and faci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Age that Minors are induced to Contract to the Destruction of their own Substance, they are also instigated and moved to fortify their Contracts with an Oath; and that many E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>states of Minors have been exhausted by the pretence of an Oath, which by snares and bad artes the captious Avarice of Contracters, and a lust of Gaining by right and wrong had extorted from their frail Age, labouring un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a Weakness of Judgement, Christnaeus <hi>vol.</hi> 5. <hi>Decis.</hi> 225. <hi>num.</hi> 20 <hi>&amp; seqq:</hi> Finellus <hi>ad l.</hi> 2. <hi>Cod. de refcind. vendit.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>num:</hi> 11. Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gentreus <hi>ad consuetudines. Britann. art.</hi> 471. <hi>num.</hi> 1. 2. Gudelinus <hi>de jure noviss. lib.</hi> 3. <hi>cap.</hi> 4. <hi>vers. non immorabor.</hi> Henr. Kinschot <hi>Responso</hi> 102. <hi>num.</hi> 18. <hi>Bugnion de legib. abrogat. libr.</hi> 1. <hi>satyra.</hi> 119. Perezius <hi>tit. Cod. si advers. vendit num. ult.</hi> and others whom Groenewegen relateth <hi>de leg. abrogat. ad</hi> D. <hi>tit. si adversus vendicionem;</hi> and Christiaenus <hi>innotis ad Bugnion.</hi> D. <hi>loco.</hi> And hence the Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>position of D. <hi>l.</hi> 1. and the Authentick. hath so far displeased the Frislanders themselves also, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though otherwayes very strict observes and Followers of the Roman Law, that it hath been Decreed by them, that sworn Renunciations and Contracts of Minors have no more effect then these that are unsworn and withal it hath been forbidden that Scriveners or Notaries do not sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject the Contracts of Minors to an Oath, or exact Oaths from them under the pain of losing their Office and other Arbitrary punishment. <hi>Satua Friziae libt.</hi> 1. <hi>tit.</hi> 7. § 5. <hi>John a sande prohibita alienatione. Cap,</hi> 1. <hi>num.</hi> 97. Unto which purpose almost, it hath been told us also that the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Scotland</hi> made an Act in the year 1681.</p>
               <closer>
                  <dateline>From all which we do not doubt, but that succour is to be given to the Minor against the sworn Transaction, about which the plea is, that he sustain not any Laesion from thence; and that so it is in Law, we judge according to our Conscience. In Testimony whereof we have subscribed these presents, and have added to our Opinion the lesser seal of the University at <hi>Ley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en</hi>
                     <date> the 7 of <hi>May</hi> 1693.</date>
                  </dateline>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <pb facs="tcp:191894:13"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>